THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
It was around the first spring breeze
在感受到春回大地的同时
that Lady Gyokuyou’s pregnancy became a certainty.
玉叶娘娘也确定怀孕了
Hi!
嘿
How mysterious. Can she tell that there’s a baby inside?
真不可思议 她知道里面有婴孩吗？
So cute!
好可爱
I should start thinking about marriage…
我也差不多该…
Even if she gets proposed to, they’ll try their best to stop it.
就算有人向她提亲 大家也会全力挽留的吧？
Being too good at your job can be a problem.
太过能干也是种困扰呢
When your days are busy, time passes quickly.
每天都过得充实
Although the two months I spent with Sir Jinshi felt like forever.
在壬氏大人那儿的两个月 明明感觉无比漫长的
Do you want to draw again?
又要画画吗？
Yeah!
对
This is woolly milkcap. It's a poisonous mushroom.
这是称作绒毛乳菇的毒菇…
Draw a regular flower.
请你画点普通的花草
A regular flower, huh?
普通的花草啊
Blue roses?
蓝色的玫瑰吗？
Yes. You don't know them?
对 你不晓得吗？
The blue petals stimulate the eyes.
能让人耳目一新的蓝色花瓣
They're very beautiful.
非常美丽呢
They used to be decorated all around the court.
据说宫里曾经开过这种花
Perhaps you were dreaming.
该不会是做梦吧？
Blue roses don’t exist.
蓝色的玫瑰并不存在吧？
But they do.
是有的
I’d love to enjoy them again.
真想和大家再一起欣赏啊
What do you think? Could you pull it off?
你觉得如何？能做点什么吗？
I thought there was nothing you couldn't achieve.
如果是你的话 应该没有办不到的事情吧？
I understand.
我知道了
If such roses exist, I’d love to see them myself.
如果真的有那种玫瑰 我也想亲自看看
So it’s decided.
就这么定了
I'm truly looking forward to it.
哎呀 真是让人期待啊
Good day, sir.
就这样吧
I’ll see you at next month’s garden party.
下个月的游园会见了
You’re already so busy.
您明明已经很忙了
-Did you need to take this on? -Don’t talk about that.
-没必要再接受额外的案件吧？ -别说了
Start by talking to flower shops around the country.
总而言之 先跟国内的花商谈谈吧
The flower shops explained that roses are out of season right now.
根据花商所言 现在并非玫瑰的季节
I’m sorry for calling upon you so suddenly.
抱歉突然把你叫来
There’s a plan to view blue roses soon.
大家决定下次要欣赏蓝色的玫瑰
Blue roses?
蓝色的玫瑰？
I work with medicine.
小的是药师啊
Yes, I know that.
对 我知道
Is he in some kind of trouble? He looks tired.
有什么隐情吗？看起来异常疲惫呢
Roses, huh?
玫瑰啊…
I have some knowledge, but…
虽然多少有点知识…
I’ve worked with roses
以前为了赚零用钱
to earn pocket money from courtesans. However…
种过一些来卖给娼妓 但…
He really said he saw blue roses?
真的有人看过蓝色的玫瑰吗？
Yes.
对
He didn’t use any hallucinogens?
该不会是正流行用迷幻药吧？
If such a thing was common, the empire would fall apart!
要是流行那种东西 国家就要灭亡啦！
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
Is it impossible?
办不到吗？
What do I need to do exactly?
您希望小的怎么做呢？
Can you have them by next month’s garden party?
能在下个月的游园会准备好吗？
Next month?
下个月？
Roses don’t bloom for at least two more months.
玫瑰要盛开至少是两个月后了
You’re right.
说得是
I’ll tell him I can’t.
我会设法回绝的
Sir Jinshi’s reaction.
壬氏大人的这个反应
This impossible task and pushy tactic…
还有把难题强塞给他的做法…
Could it be that this request came from a certain military man?
这件事 该不会是 某个军师提起的吧？
That’s right.
没错
All right. I accept this job.
明白了 小的愿意接下
Really?
可以吗？
I don’t know if I can do it, but I’ll do what I can.
不知道能不能办到 但小的会尽力
I don't want to be running away from him forever.
一味逃避也只会让人生气
I'd love to crack that smirking monocle of his.
倒不如趁这机会 打烂那个奸笑的单片眼镜
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
Can I request some items from you?
小的能向您请求几样东西吗？
Thank you for giving me permission to use these,
谢谢您同意让小的使用
-Lady Lihua. -It was no trouble.
梨花娘娘
It was originally something you had made.
那原本就是你造出来的
It brings me back.
真是怀念
I requested a steam bath to be made
之前为了帮中毒卧床的梨花娘娘养病
to help Lady Lihua recover from poison.
而建造了一间蒸气浴堂
I'll be borrowing the bath for this job,
这次虽然是为了差事
but I would feel bad borrowing it for free.
但白白借用也不太好意思
This is the Emperor's favorite text.
这是陛下爱看的书
Thank you. This will help.
谢谢你呀
I'm glad I had it delivered from the brothel.
还好之前向青楼订了书呢
-Take care of that. -Yes, sir!
-那边麻烦了 -是！
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
Oh, you're here.
哦 你来了
I had this made, like you asked. But what is it for?
我照你说的盖好了 但这是要做什么呢？
I'm going to confuse the roses.
要让玫瑰失常
Confuse the roses?
让玫瑰失常？
What does that mean, Apothecary?
这是什么意思 药师？
I'll add some sunlight
引进日光
and add some steam into the shed from there.
再从那儿将蒸气送进小屋
We'll grow the roses in a warm room.
在温暖的房间里种植玫瑰
The flowers may bloom ahead of season this way.
花朵也许就会误认开花的季节到了
So that's what you mean by confusing the roses.
这就是失常吗？
I'm not certain this will work, though.
不保证会开花就是了
Maomao!
猫猫！
-Xiaolan? -I'll help too.
-小兰？ -我也来帮忙
How's your injured foot?
你的脚伤还好吗？
Is he a chaperone?
该不会是在监督吧？
They kept saying
被说了好几次
not to push myself repeatedly.
别勉强自己的关系吧
I'm all right. Thanks for coming to help.
我没事 抱歉要你来帮忙
Not at all. It's been so long since I worked with you!
不会啦 好久没一起工作了呢
You're right.
真的呢
We carried in more than 100 pots of roses.
搬进来的玫瑰超过一百株
This is the last one.
这是最后一个了
Wow, there are so many!
哇 好多哦
We got different types of roses,
我们挑了各种玫瑰
and selected species that bloom earlier in the year.
并尽可能选了会提早开花的品种
You think they'll all bloom?
全部都会开花吗？
I hope so.
希望是如此
We take great care in maintaining the temperature.
温度需要相当细心的调整
A few people were sent to help us,
虽然派了几名人手过来帮忙
but it's a hard task to leave to someone else.
但这件工作很难交给别人
If you make a mistake
一旦不小心
and all the flowers die, then everything is over.
让全部的花枯萎就完了
We put the flowers out on sunny days so they can absorb sunlight.
在晴天时 我们会将 玫瑰搬到室外照射日光
Looks like they like the sun!
感觉好像很舒服
Yeah.
对啊
How is it going?
状况如何？
I brought some food.
这是慰劳的点心
Thank you.
谢谢您
This is great! I don't have to work, and we get snacks!
不仅能躲掉差事 还有点心可以吃
This is work too.
这也是工作啊
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I don't know. Maybe they're just curious.
不晓得 可能觉得稀奇吧？
Or, are they trying to see something scary?
还是越害怕越想看呢？
What should we do next?
接下来要做什么？
If there are seedlings with too many buds,
如果有幼苗长了太多新芽
can you pluck some out?
能帮我摘一点下来吗？
That way, the nutrients gather in one spot making it easier to bloom
这样能集中养分 更容易开花
and protects it from diseases.
还能防止生病
It's totally fine!
没事啦
-Thank you so much. -Not at all!
-非常谢谢你 -不会
Hurry up!
快点
They're not budding yet.
好像结不出花苞呢
On the days the cold returns,
在变回寒冷的日子
we keep the shed warm all night.
就得彻夜帮小屋加温
The weather is unpredictable.
天气是无法控制的
You didn't sleep again yesterday?
你昨天也没睡吗？
I slept at dawn.
天亮时有睡一下
That was only moments ago!
不是刚刚才天亮吗？
I'll do what I can here, so you should sleep just a little.
我会做我能做的事 你去稍微睡一下吧？
I should keep an eye on them.
必须盯着才行啊
What?
嗯？
They're looking over here again.
她们又在看这儿了
They do this every day! Don't they get tired of it?
每天都来不腻啊？
It's very distracting.
实在让人分心
If only I could divert their attention…
有什么能转移她们的注意力…
Wow!
好厉害
So these are rouge nails!
这就是染指甲啊
Everyone at the pleasure district does these.
在花街很常见哦
They're very beautiful!
因为很漂亮吧？
You do your nails too, Maomao?
猫猫也染了吗？
They're so cute!
好可爱
They're very trendy these days.
最近好像很流行呢
Yes, they are.
对啊
High-ranking concubines who receive the Emperor's affections
受到皇帝宠爱的上级妃
are the creators of fashion trends.
可说是时尚的最尖端
They're very inefficient.
真是影响效率啊
Ms. Hongniang cares more about work than fashion.
红娘大人比起时尚更注重工作啊
I'm done with the food testing, so I'll head back to the Crystal Pavilion.
试毒已经结束 小的先回水晶宫了
So soon?
又要回去？
There's not much time left until the garden party.
距离游园会没剩多少时间了
That's true.
的确
That reminds me.
对了
Lady Gyokuyou will not be attending this party.
这次玉叶娘娘不会出席
She'll be giving up her seat so that Lady Loulan can introduce herself.
楼兰娘娘要初次亮相 所以得礼让她才行
It must be to hide her pregnancy.
是为了隐藏怀孕的事吧？
I understand. Goodbye.
明白了 小的先告辞了
Hey, are you all right at the Crystal pavilion?
喂 你在水晶宫没问题吗？
You're getting skinnier by the day!
你越来越消瘦了呢
Don't push yourself, all right?
别太勉强自己了
Thank you.
谢谢你们
Maomao!
猫猫！
Maomao, come quickly!
猫猫 不得了了！
It's budding.
花苞
I found it just now.
我刚刚发现的
It's our first one!
终于结出一个了！
If everything goes as planned,
这样继续下去
maybe they'll start to bloom…
应该就会开花了吧？
Maomao?
猫猫？
Any messages from the Apothecary?
药师那边有消息吗？
No.
没有
I haven't been able to drop by for a few days.
我这几天也没能去露脸
We were both busy preparing for the garden party.
我们都忙着准备游园会啊
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
That must be Sir Shishou's daughter, Concubine Loulan.
那就是子昌大人的女儿 楼兰妃吗？
How glamorous!
真是艳丽啊
For Concubine Loulan.
楼兰妃
If she has any shortcomings,
不晓得是否任何不妥之处呢？
please let us know.
无论是什么 都请告诉我们
-Anything at all. -Oh, dear.
-什么都可以 -嗯
-Blue roses? -Could it be?
-蓝色的玫瑰？ -怎么可能？
Perhaps it'll be agreeable
先欣赏花苞
to enjoy these buds and imagine what they will look like
想象它们盛开的样子
when they bloom.
也是一种乐趣
Yes. They are beautiful.
嗯 相当漂亮呢
These glances that are thrown at "Jinshi."
这些投向“壬氏”的不同目光
No matter how beautiful he may be,
不管他的容貌多么姣好
no official is so unselfish that they'd enjoy a young eunuch
并非所有官员都无欲无求
showing off his abilities.
愿意看到一位年轻宦官锋芒毕露
Lust is easy.
情欲倒好
You can use it to your advantage.
利用方法多的是
Jealousy is easy. It's easy to manage.
嫉妒也罢 不难应付
What's bothersome is
但麻烦的是
when you can't read the emotion behind those eyes.
那一双看不出在想什么的眼睛
Shishou. Concubine Loulan's father,
子昌 楼兰妃的生父
and the man who won the empress's affection.
受到女帝宠信的男人
The emperor still owes much to him.
直到现在 皇帝也得让他三分
That's why our side continues to smile.
也因此 这儿只能保持微笑
And right now, we have someone more concerning than Shishou.
而且现在 还有个比子昌更棘手的家伙
It's that man, Lakan.
那个男人 罗汉
My, how disagreeable.
真是不快啊
Are you awake?
你醒了吗？
Ms. Yinghua…
樱花大人
Don't go to the Crystal Pavilion anymore.
你不可以再去水晶宫了
You always come back all skinny and tired.
你每次回来都操劳过度
I'm sorry.
抱歉
You're awake?
你醒了啊
I'll be going now.
我先告辞了
Stay seated.
坐着吧
It was very hard.
很困难呢
We couldn't get them to bloom in time.
没有办法及时让花盛开
But it's not like you wanted to impress me, did you?
你应该不是在向我道歉吧？
Huh?
什么？
It's nothing. It was more than enough.
没什么 这样很够了
How did you achieve this?
这到底是怎么做的？
I just dyed them.
只是染了色而已
You dyed them? But there's nothing there.
染色？但什么都没沾着啊
It's not dyed on the outside.
并不是从外侧
It's dyed from the inside.
而是从内侧染的
These roses were all originally white.
这些玫瑰原本全是白色的花
We used different types of colored water
我们做了各种染色的水
and soaked the white buds in them.
然后让白色花苞吸收
So that's why there were many colors, not just blue.
所以才不只有蓝色 还有许多颜色啊
Yes. The leaves get muddy and dark when they're dyed,
对 但叶片染得又黑又脏
so we plucked them all in advance.
所以我事先都摘了下来
After that, we fixed some cotton soaked with colored water so that
再来 为了避免在游园会当中褪色
the color doesn't come off during the garden party.
用沾过颜料水的棉花固定后便完成了
It's very simple.
说起来其实非常单纯
In actuality,
实际上
The truly hard part was getting the roses to bloom in time.
最费工夫的还是让玫瑰开花这一关
Yes, it's very simple.
确实是非常单纯
That's why there may be
因为如此
officials who complain and make accusations.
也许有官员会鸡蛋里挑骨头
I explained the trick to the Emperor in advance.
我便事先跟皇帝说明了情况
He seemed to enjoy knowing the secret beforehand,
他似乎很高兴能第一个知道秘密
and listened to me explain it with interest.
兴致勃勃地听着解释呢
So why did he say he used to see blue roses in the court?
那么 宫里以前见过的蓝色玫瑰是？
There must've been some bored person
大概是有个闲人
soaking blue-colored water into the roses every day.
日复一日让玫瑰吸取蓝色的水吧
Why would they do such a thing?
为什么要做这种事？
Who knows?
不清楚
Maybe they wanted something to flirt with women with.
也许是想弄个小东西讨女人欢心吧？
I haven't seen you with dyed nails before.
真难得 你染了指甲？
It doesn't suit me.
不太适合就是了
If I had some balsam or wood sorrel, the dye would apply more evenly.
要是有凤仙花和酢浆草 就能染得更漂亮了
Balsam are known as "rouge nails,"
别名“指甲花”的凤仙花
and sorrel are known as "cat's feet."
以及别名“猫足”的酢浆草
If you rub these plants together, it makes a vibrant red color for your nails..
捣碎融合涂在指甲上 就能让红色更为鲜艳
Though a little nail dye wouldn't change this…
不过 染上了漂亮的颜色后
At least it's better than it used to be.
这看起来也算是象样了
Sir Gaoshun, do you have the requested items?
高顺大人 小的拜托您的东西呢？
Yes, just as you asked.
是 照你说的办妥了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢您
Now, the stage is set.
这样舞台就布置好了
All that's left is to
接下来
blow away that despicable man.
就是让讨厌鬼大吃一惊了
I didn't think that the challenge would end in failure.
没想到我的挑衅会以失败告终啊
Most humans look like Go pieces to me.
大多数人在我看来只是围棋的模样
Men are the black stones, and women are the white stones.
男人是黑子 女人是白子
Even the men who work for me in the military
即使是军府的部下
are all just xiangqi pieces.
顶多也就是变成了象棋
Most are soldiers, or pawns.
大多数人是兵、卒
As they rise up the ranks, they become horses, or cannon.
随着军阶上升变成了马、砲等
Working in the military is quite simple.
军府的工作很简单
You simply have to place the pieces where they belong.
只要把棋子放到适合的地方即可
Everyone has their roles.
适材适用
That's how you win most wars.
这样就能赢下大多数的战争
It's not difficult at all.
这没什么难的
Even if you are unskilled, as long as the pieces fulfill their roles,
即使自己无能 只要把差事分配出去
they'll finish your job for you.
旁人就会自动把事情做完
My eyes hurt more than usual.
今天比平常更伤眼呢
I keep noticing red flickering around in my vision.
眼前到处都是红色
Rouge nails, huh?
染指甲吗？
The rouge nails I remember aren't a distasteful, flashy red.
我记忆中的红指甲 并不是那样俗艳的红色
It's a subtle red, dyed from balsam.
而是淡淡染上一层的凤仙花红
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next Episode, "Balsam and Wood Sorrel."
下一集 《凤仙花与酢浆草》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易